Finding Aid for the Pamela Gearhart Collection of Audio Recordings, 1954-1975
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
Pamela Gearhart Collection of Audio Recordings, 1954-1975
Mus. Arc. 33.2
Gearhart, Pamela
1 box (20 audio cassettes) and 1 12-inch sound disc
State University of New York at Buffalo. Music Library
The collection contains 20 audio cassettes with recordings of performances by Pamela Gearhart, as well as two interviews. The LP recording contains a performance by Gearhart's father, Russell Gerhart, conducting the Huntsville, Alabama Symphony Orchestra.
Administrative Information
Terms of Access
Materials can be examined by qualified researchers in the Music Library during hours of operation during which Music Librarians are present. In order to insure access, researchers are advised to contact the Music Library in advance of visits.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the estate of Pamela Gearhart, 2014.
Accruals and Additions
No further accruals are expected to this collection.
Biographical Note
Pamela Gearhart (née Gerhart) was born July 21, 1934 in Altoona, Pennsylvania. She began her musical training with her father, violinist and conductor, Russell Gerhart. Russell Gerhart studied violin with Ralph Lewando, Carl Malcherek, Elias Breeskin, and Mischa Mischakoff. He studied conducting with Serge Koussevitsky at the Berkshire Music Center. Gerhart and his wife Martha formed the Gerhart String Ensemble in Altoona, Pennsylvania, which grew into the Altoona Symphony Orchestra. He also served as conductor of the Saint Louis Philharmonic and Huntsville (Alabama) Civic Symphony.
When Pamela Gearhart was fifteen she began five years of study at the Curtis Institute of Music in Philadelphia. Her violin teachers before and after her years at Curtis were Mischa Mischakoff, Joseph Knitzer, Ivan Galamian and Efrem Zimbalist. While at Curtis she performed in the Curtis Orchestra under conductors Alexander Hilsberg and William Smith, and studied chamber music performance with Karen Tuttle and Marcel Tabuteau.
Gearhart was appointed faculty member in the University of Buffalo Music Department in 1957. Initially she was hired as a part-time instructor in violin but eventually assumed other duties, including conducting the university's orchestra and directing the program in chamber music performance. She continued to work at the University at Buffalo until 1975.
While in Buffalo Gearhart also served as conductor of the Community Music School of Buffalo's youth orchestra 1959-1977. The membership in the orchestra grew from ten to more than one hundred while she was conductor. Her credentials as a music educator also include work on the faculty at Villa Maria Institute of Music (Buffalo) 1963-1965, serving for six years as Alexander Schneider's assistant for the University at Buffalo's String Institute, numerous positions as guest conductor and judge at music festivals, and director of the Youth Makes Music String Workshop (Huntsville, Alabama). After leaving the University at Buffalo she joined the faculty at Ithaca College where she taught 1975-1993. In 1980 she founded the Ithaca Youth Orchestra. She continued as its conductor until her retirement from Ithaca College.
Pamela Gearhart married fellow University at Buffalo music faculty member Livingston Gearhart in 1955. They were frequent collaborators on programs and projects. Livingston wrote many musical arrangements geared specifically to the pedagogical needs of Pamela's ensembles. Many of these arrangements and compositions survive in the Livingston Gearhart Score Collection. Pamela Gearhart died July 6 2014 in Rochester, New York.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains 20 audio cassettes with recordings of performances by Pamela Gearhart, as well as two interviews. The LP recording contains a performance by Gearhart's father, Russell Gerhart, conducting the Huntsville, Alabama Symphony Orchestra.
Pamela Gearhart is listed throughout the container list as "Gearhart" rather than risking confusion listing her under her maiden name of Gerhart for recordings prior to her marriage to Livingston Gearhart in 1955.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series:
I. Audio cassettes
II. Long-playing 12-inch sound disc
Container List
- Cassettes, 1954-1975, I.; Items 1-20
  Arranged in rough chronological order.
  - Mozart in D minor Quartet, 1954, 1 audio cassette; Inscription on cassette: P.G. Curtis [Institute of Music] 1954. (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Excerpts from performances of St. Louis Philharmonic and String ensemble, Russell Gerhart conducting, circa 1955, 1 audio cassette; Russell Gerhart was principal conductor of the St. Louis Philharmonic 1951-1958. (Box 1, Item 1)
  - Mendelssohn concerto, 1955 January 20, 1 audio cassette; Inscription on cassette spine: Swiss lullaby. (Box 1, Item 3)
    Performed by Pamela Gearhart, violin, St. Louis Philharmonic, Russell Gerhart, conductor.
  - P.G. 1957 Toch rehearsal, 1957 August 5, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 4)
    Serenade Spitzweg / Ernest Toch -- Kodaly -- L'histoire.
    Performers: Mr. Taub, Mrs. Gearhart, Mr. Juvelier.
  - Schneider-Handel concert, P.G., circa 1958-1965, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 5)
  - Kodaly: Kim and Pam, circa 1958, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 6)
    Probably performance of the Kodaly Duo for violin and cello, op. 7 by Pamela Gearhart, violin, and Kim Williamson, cello.
  - Dances and finale (L'histoire) / Stravinsky; Duo (with Mimi Denton) / Mozart; Duo (with Kim Williamson) / Kodaly, circa 1958, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 7)
  - Romance in f major / Beethoven; Introduction and Rondo capriccioso / Saint Saens; Perpetual motion, 1961 January 16, 1 audio cassette; Inscription on cassette spine: P.G. Huntsville performance. (Box 1, Item 8)
    Performers: Pamela Gearhart, violin; Huntsville Civic Orchestra; Russell Gerhart, conductor.
  - Variations on an American air / Livingston Gearhart, 1962 August 14, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 9)
    Performers: Chautauqua Symphony Orchestra; Walter Hendl, conductor.
  - Villa Maria concert, 1965, 1 audio cassette; Inscription on cassette spine: Villa Maria 1963 - Elementary string demo. (Box 1, Item 10)
    Label attached to cassette case: Slavic tune, Chorale prelude. These two works are from Livingston Gearhart's proposed publication, String mix II.
  - UB strings, 1967, 1973, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 11)
    Corelli: Xmas concerto (Judy and P.G.?) -- Debussy: Danse harp -- Bach: Fantasia oboe -- Bloch: L.G. piano -- Hindemith: op. 47 no. 2 and no. 3; op. 44 no. 2 -- Corelli: op. 6 no. 8 (Judy and JoAnn) -- L[ivingston] G[earhart]: Short suite.
  - CMS, 1968, 1 audio cassette; Inscription on cassette spine:. (Box 1, Item 12)
    Community Music School youth orchestra, conducted by Pamela Gearhart.
    Liadoff -- Mendelssohn: Reformation, slow mvt. -- Bizet: Carmen -- Faure: Pavane -- Vivaldi: A minor (multi violin soloists) -- We shall overcome (orchestra and chorus).
  - UB Fauré Requiem, 1969, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 13)
    Side B of tape contains performances in 1973 with the UB Chamber Orchestra in Buffalo of Poulenc Organ concerto, one at First Presbyterian Church, the other at St. Paul's.
  - CMS, 1970, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 14)
    Side A: Wagner: 3 excerpts -- Bruch: Kol nidrei -- Liadoff -- Stravinsky: Suite -- Bach: Komm susser tod -- Vivaldi: Solo celli -- Tsch. Suite no. 3.
    Side B of tape contains CMS 1974: P.G. speech -- Sousa march.
  - P.G. and pupils, Radio WBFO, 1970, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 15)
  - Chamber orch, 1973, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 16)
    Mozart F major -- Stravinsky: Dumbarton oaks -- Poulenc: Organ concerto.
  - YMCF, 1973, 1974, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 17)
    Mozart: F major -- Couperin: Saraband -- Bach: Brandenburg 3. 1st mov. -- Mozart: D major -- Copland: Lento -- Bach: Art of fugue. Contrapunctus no. IX -- Ravel: 3 chansons. Slow mvt. only -- Tsch.: Serenade. 1st mov.
  - UB, 1974, 1 audio cassette; Inscription on cassette spine: L.G. prepared piano. (Box 1, Item 18)
    Kodaly: Hary Janos (L.G. piano) -- Stravinsky: Apollon musagète (UB chamber orchestra 1972).
  - Interview with Pamela Gearhart about the University of Buffalo Orchestra, circa 1975, 1 audio cassette; WBFO by Walter J. Gajewski. (Box 1, Item 19)
  - UB strings, 1975, 1 audio cassette (Box 1, Item 20)
    Side A: Bach: Mein Jesu -- Ravel: Trois chansons -- Carter: Elegy -- Pedrollo: Concerto -- Bach: Old year all men -- Side B. YMCF 1973. Bach: Fuga; Ricercata.
- Long-playing 12-inch sound disc, 1970, II.; Item 21
  - Russell Gerhart conducts, 1970, 1 12-inch 33 1/3 rpm sound disc; Clarence, New York: Mark Custom Records. Publisher number: MC5792. Inscribed by Pamela Gearhart to "Dorothy". (Box 2, Item 21)
    Rustic wedding symphony / Goldmark.
Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog.
Contributors
Gearhart, Livingston; Gerhart, Russell, 1902-1972
Subjects
Women conductors (Music)--New York (State); Women violinists--New York (State)
Genres
Sound recordings
Associated Material
Related Resources
Related Resources in the Music Library
Pamela Gearhart Papers, 1956-1993
Mus. Arc. 33
The Pamela Gearhart Papers contain a biographical summary, curriculum vitae, correspondence, newspaper clippings, and programs.
Pamela Gearhart Photograph Collection, 1957-1997
Mus. Arc. 33.1
The collection contains 216 photographs, including images of Russell Gerhart, Franco Autori, Claudette Sorel, Edward Murphy, Mischa Mischakoff, Livingston Gearhart, Alexander and Mischa Schneider, Skitch Henderson, and Pamela Gearhart.
Livingston Gearhart Papers, 1933-1997
Mus. Arc. 23.1
The collection contains prose writings, vitae, correspondence, teaching materials, programs, and clippings.
Livingston Gearhart Recordings, 1949-2001
Mus. Arc. 23.4
The collection contains reel to reel and cassette tapes, compact discs, and LPs containing music composed or arranged by Livingston Gearhart.